A Guide to the Newport and Clover Hollow, Giles County History Collection, 1904, 1973-2006
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Newport and Clover Hollow, Giles County History Collection, 1904, 1973-2006
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2013-086
4.9 cu. ft. 5 boxes
The Newport and Clover Hollow, Giles County History collection contains oral history interviews, transcripts, notes, newspaper clippings, historic district survey forms, a video tape, and a geological survey map related to the creation of the Greater Newport Rural Historic District. The collection dates from 1973 to 2009, although it does include a typed copy of a 1904 Giles County will.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Historic materials, photographs, data sheets, and other forms are open for research. Oral histories and transcripts are currently restricted. Please contact Special Collections for more information.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to Special Collections in December 2007.
Historical Note
Newport and Clover Hollow are located in Giles County, Virginia. They form part of the Greater Newport Rural Historic District, which is located in the Eastern District of Giles County. Listed in the National Registrar of Historic Places in 2000, the Greater Newport Rural Historic District includes five distinct sections: Sinking Creek, Spruce Run, Clover Hollow, Plowscrew, and Mountain Lake. The historic district is agricultural and rural in character, consisting mostly of nineteenth and early-twentieth century farmsteads. Overall, the district includes approximately 21,085 acres.
Closely associated with the effort to designate this area as a rural historic district was the struggle by community members against AEP's proposed powerline. In March 1990, the contestation over proposed powerline routes was initiated when the energy company Apco -- which would change its name to AEP during the course of the powerline battle -- announced its plans to build a transmission line from West Virginia to Cloverdale. The estimated date for its completion was 1998. Following this announcement, opposition arose from communities along the proposed route. In Giles County, Virginia, concerned community members joined together to create the organization Citizens Organized to Protect the Environment (COPE), which fought against the proposed powerline. For more detailed information on the powerline struggle and establishment of the Greater Newport Rural Historical District see the following:
Carlisle, Fred. "Insiders, Outsiders, and the Struggle for Community," Appalachian Journal, Vol. 26, No. 3 (Spring 1999), 240-251.
Carlisle, Fred. "The Past in the Present: The Greater Newport Rural Historic District," Appalachian Journal, Vol. 32, No. 1 (Fall 2004), 50-66.
Sources Consulted:
"Greater Newport Rural Historic District, Giles County, Virginia," http://www.cr.nps.gov/NR/publications/bulletins/01workshop/newport.htm
Scope and Content Note
The Newport and Clover Hollow, Giles County History collection contains oral history interviews, transcripts, notes, newspaper clippings, historic district survey forms, a video tape, and a geological survey map related to the creation of the Greater Newport Rural Historic District. The collection dates from 1973 to 2009, although it does include a typed copy of a 1904 Giles county will. The materials in this collection not only reveal information on the history and people of Giles county, but they also document the community's efforts to get Newport designated as a rural agricultural historic district. Most of the newspaper clippings concern the threat of AEP building a new powerline that would have cut across the Newport area.
Some transcripts appear to be mixed into the wrong file, however, as this was the way in which material was presented, original order was maintained.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into five series based on subject and material type: Series I: Oral Histories; Series II: Newport Rural Historic District Materials; Series III: Photographs; Series IV: Data Sheets; and Series V: IPS Forms for GNRHD.
Series I: Oral Histories contains two subseries. Subseries I: Transcripts includes typed transcripts of oral histories. Subseries II: Interviews contains the oral histories on cassette tape. Please note: Series I is currently restricted, pending release forms for interviews.
Series II: Newport Rural Historic District Materials consists of publications, newspaper clippings and articles, and other resources on the history of the Newport region.
Series III: Photographs contains photocopies of images submitted with applications for historic status, as well as original photographs of different geographical areas around Newport and Clover Hollow. Series IV: Data Sheets includes related information about the areas depicted in the photographs.
Series V: IPS Forms for GNRHD consists of copies of forms submitted for Virginia Division of Historic Landmark status. In addition to Newport and Clover Hollow, other forms relate to Mountain Lake.
Materials were organized into series based on type/format. All series were left in their original order, though the photographs and data sheets were removed from binders.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Materials
The following books have been removed from the collection and catalogued for the Rare Book Collection:
Hiss, Tony. The Experience of Place: A new way of looking at and dealing with our radically changing cities and countryside. New York: Vintage Books, 1990.
Givens, Nancy Kate. The Red Bridge: A collection of article, stories and facts about the 1916 Covered Bridge spanning Sinking Creek by Clover Hollow Road. 2007.
Johnson, Patricia Givens. Confederate Women of New River Border Country. Blacksburg, VA: Walpa Publishing, 1993.
Kapp, Paul Hardin. Greater Newport Rural Historic District: Architectural Survey, Giles County, Virginia. 1999.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Giles County (Va.); Local/Regional History and Appalachian South
Contents List
- Series I: Oral Histories
  Access Restrictions
  This series is currently restricted. Please contact Special Collections for more information.
  - Subseries I: Transcripts
    - Transcripts and Notes: David Brady, Tom Brobson, Mike Dawson, 1996 (Box-folder 1-1)
    - Ed Givens Transcript, 1995 (Box-folder 1-2)
    - Tillie Lucas Transcripts, 1997 (Box-folder 1-3)
    - Transcripts of Conversations with Doris Link, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 1-4)
    - Vincel Transcripts: Assorted Notes & Material, 1995-2000 (Box-folder 1-5)
    - Vincel Transcripts: Bill & Caroline, 1995, n.d. (Box-folder 1-6)
    - Vincel Transcripts: Ed Givens, 1995 (Box-folder 1-7)
    - Lucas Transcripts: Assorted Notes & Material, 1995 (Box-folder 1-8)
    - Lucas Transcripts: Doak Lucas and Alva Lucas, 1995 (Box-folder 1-9)
    - Transcripts and Notes from Conversations with Mark Givens and Mary Givens - His Mother, 1996 (Box-folder 1-10)
    - Nancy Sibold Transcripts, 1995 (Box-folder 1-11)
    - Vincel and Lucas Transcripts, n.d. (Box-folder 1-12)
    - Transcripts: Link, Martin, Miller, 1995 (Box-folder 1-13)
    - Transcripts: Marty Farrier, Cliff Shaffer, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 1-14)
    - Lafon Transcripts & Notes, 1997 (Box-folder 1-15)
    - Transcript - Bill & Caroline Vincel, February 6th and 7th (Box-folder 2-9)
  - Subseries II: Interviews (Box 1)
    - Brady, David, March, 6, 2006 (Cassette 1)
    - Tillie & Marjorie Lucas, November 24, 1996 (Cassette 2-3)
    - Lucas, Tillie, March 5, 1997; December 3, 1997 (Cassette 4-5)
    - Jim & Gail Lucas, n.d. (Cassette 6)
    - Lucas, Jim (Cassette 7)
    - Lucas, Doak, February 1, 1995 (Cassette 8)
    - Doak & Alva Lucas, February 20, 1995 (Cassette 9)
    - Doak & Alva Interview - Kurstedt Interview, n.d. (Cassette 10)
    - Stewart & Victor Link, November 29, 1995 (Cassette 11)
    - Link, Doris, May 18, 2000 (Cassette 12)
    - Johnson, Patricia Givens, March 23, 1995? 1996? (Cassette 13)
    - Givens, Nancy Kate, April 2000 (Cassette 14)
    - Givens, Mark, July 19, 1996; July 22, 1996; April 3, 1996 (Cassette 15-17)
    - Givens, Ed, February 15 and 16, 1995 (Cassette 18-19)
    - Lafon, April 13, 1997 (Cassette 20)
    - Wade & Annie (Dodgin) Lafon, April 13, 1997 (Cassette 21)
    - Lafon, Wade, January 19, 1997 (Cassette 22)
    - Ferrier, Marty, February 24, 1996 (Cassette 23)
    - Domermuth, Dorothy, April 4, 2000 (Cassette 24)
    - Brady & Brobson, July 26, 1996 (Cassette 25)
    - Brady, David, August 5, 1996 (Cassette 26)
    - Pat & Lyn Bohmer, June 21, 2000 (Cassette 27)
    - Dawson, Mike, March 21, 2001 (Cassette 28)
    - Godfrey, H. D., March 20, 2001 (Cassette 29)
    - Vincel, May 19, 1998; January 1996; July 27, 1995; February 14, 1995; February 7 & 14, 1995; February 6 & 7, 1995; February 7, 1995 (Cassette 30-36)
    - Ulrich, Greg & Lovene, May 6, 2000 (Cassette 37)
    - Snider, Karen, August 18, 1998 (Cassette 38)
    - Shaffer, Cliff, January 17, 1997 (Cassette 39)
    - Sibold, Nancy, June 19, 1998; February 19, 1996; March 28, 1995 (Cassette 40-43)
    - Miller, Hattie, April 13, 1995 (Cassette 44)
    - Wilbur, Martin, May 24, 1995 (Cassette 45)
- Series II: Newport Rural Historic District Materials
  - Papers Related to Greater Newport Rural Historic District (GNRHD), 1995-1997 (Box-folder 3-11)
  - Applications: Newport Historic District - Grant, Original Rural, Newport, 1995-1998 (Box-folder 2-1)
  - Copy GNRHD Nomination, Corrected, December 3, 1999 (Box-folder 2-2)
  - Post Office, Church, Schools, Cemeteries, 2001 (Box-folder 2-3)
  - Post Office, Church, Schools, Cemeteries: Banks, 2001 (Box-folder 2-4)
  - Post Office, Church, Schools, Cemeteries: Moses Atkins, 2001 (Box-folder 2-5)
  - Post Office, Church, Schools, Cemeteries: Post Office, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 2-6)
  - Post Office, Church, Schools, Cemeteries: Church, 2001 (Box-folder 2-7)
  - Miscellaneous Papers Related to the Powerline Fight, 1997-2000 (Box-folder 2-8)
  - Informational Materials on Rural Historical Districts & "Clover Hollow Memories," 1984-2000 (Box-folder 2-10)
  - Newport Tall Tales, 1996 (Box-folder 2-11)
  - GNRHD: Clover Hollow, 1996-2001 (Box-folder 2-12)
  - Clover Hollow, 1989-1996 (Box-folder 2-13)
  - GNRHD Planning Materials, 1904, 1990-2002 (Box-folder 2-14)
  - Powerline Articles, 1996-1998 (Box-folder 2-15)
  - Articles and Papers Related to COPE and the Powerline Struggle, 1993-1998 (Box-folder 2-16)
  - Newport Agricultural Fair Booklets, 1993-1996 (Box-folder 2-17)
  - Newport Agricultural Fair Booklets, 1998-2000 (Box-folder 2-18)
  - "A Story of Newport and its People," (Part 1 of 2), n.d. (Box-folder 2-19)
  - "A Story of Newport and its People," (Part 2 of 2), n.d. (Box-folder 2-20)
  - Greater Newport Rural Historic District Map, 1985 (Box-folder 4-9)
  - "A Tour of the Greater Newport Rural Historic District" Video Cassette, Summer 1996 (Box-folder 4-10)
- Series III: Photographs
  - Copies of Photographs Submitted with Application: Sinking Creek & Clover Hollow, 1996 (Box-folder 2-21)
  - Copies of Photographs Submitted with Application: Plowscrew, Mountain Lake Road, & Highway 460, 1996 (Box-folder 2-22)
  - Copies of Photographs Submitted with Application: Spruce Run, 1996 (Box-folder 2-23)
  - Pictures, Book 1: Sinking Creek, Blue Grass Trail, 1996 (Box-folder 2-24)
  - Pictures, Book 1: Sinking Creek, Highways 601 and 604, 1996 (Box-folder 2-25)
  - Pictures, Book 1: Clover Hollow, 1996 (Box-folder 2-26)
  - Pictures, Book 2: Plow Screw, 1996 (Box-folder 2-27)
  - Pictures, Book 2: Highway 460, Highway 796, 1996 (Box-folder 2-28)
  - Pictures, Book 2: Mountain Lake Road, 1996 (Box-folder 3-1)
  - Pictures, Book 3: Spruce Run, 1996 (Box-folder 3-2)
- Series IV: Data Sheets
  - Data Sheets: Sinking Creek, (Part 1 of 2), 1996 (Box-folder 3-3)
  - Data Sheets: Sinking Creek, (Part 2 of 2), 1996 (Box-folder 3-4)
  - Data Sheets: Clover Hollow, 1996 (Box-folder 3-5)
  - Data Sheets: Plow Screw, n.d. (Box-folder 3-6)
  - Data Sheets: Mountain Lake, n.d. (Box-folder 3-7)
  - Data Sheets: Spruce Run, (Part 1 of 2), n.d. (Box-folder 3-8)
  - Data Sheets: Spruce Run, (Part 2 of 2), n.d. (Box-folder 3-9)
  - Historic District Back Up, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 3-10)
- Series V: IPS Forms for GNRHD
  - IPS Forms: File Numbers 35-151-1 to 35-151-11, 1989 (Box-folder 5-1)
  - IPS Forms: File Numbers 35-151-12 to 35-151-24, 1989 (Box-folder 5-2)
  - IPS Form: File Number 35-59, 1973-1989 (Box-folder 5-3)
  - Numbered IPS Forms: 1-130, 1998 (Box-folder 4-1)
  - Numbered IPS Forms: 131-255, 1998 (Box-folder 4-2)
  - Numbered IPS Forms: 256-376, 1996-1998 (Box-folder 4-3)
  - Numbered IPS Forms: 377-417, 1996-1998 (Box-folder 4-4)
  - IPS Forms: Ed Sibold Farm, 1998 (Box-folder 4-5)
  - IPS Forms: Mountain Lake Resort, 1998 (Box-folder 4-6)
  - IPS Forms: Mountain Lake Biological Station, 1998 (Box-folder 4-7)
  - Blank Virginia Division of Historic Landmarks Survey Form, n.d. (Box-folder 4-8)